Online, there we have a new דף daf up on the web,
or up on the, whatever, the server. Okay, but we start with
the משנה mishna on י"ב עמוד ב'. Yud Bais Amud Bais. As
you see, it's a short דף daf coming up and I'll explain
why in a minute. Let's read the משנה. mishna. Okay, so we're
in the middle of discussing פיגול, pigul, we had this interesting little
digression about the effect of a פיגול pigul thought when you don't
have the whole שיריים shiurayim left. But now we get back to
central elements of פיגול. pigul. What did we resolve out of that?
Nothing, right? Nothing. Exactly. לאכול כחצי זית ולהקטיר
כחצי זית.
Le'echol k'chatzi zayit
u'lehaktir k'chatzi zayit.
Let's say you are intending when you take the, when you take
the קומץ, komets, you're having in mind that you're going to eat
half of a כזית kezayit at the wrong time and you're going
to burn half of a כזית kezayit of the קומץ komets at
the wrong time. So each act by itself is not a significant
act. Can you combine the two? So it says כשר, kasher, not
only is it not פיגול, pigul, the קרבן korban is כשר, kasher,
it was not a thought about a meaningful act because each act
by itself was not meaningful. And שאין אכילה והקטרה מצטרפין. she'ein achilah
v'haktarah mitztarpin. They don't combine because an act of eating is not
related to an act of burning. If you thought like I'm going
to eat half of a כזית kezayit on Tuesday and another half
of a כזית kezayit on Wednesday, then that probably would combine although
you start to have interesting questions about כדי אכילת פרס k'dei achilat
pras and so on, you know, it's the whole issue about thought
combining actions, not actions combining themselves, but at least there you're talking
about two acts of eating and in the total you have an
eating of a כזית. kezayit. Here you have an eating and a
burning, each one is not an action by itself and they don't
combine because they are separate acts. So now we're going to let's
see what the גמרא Gemara has to say on this. טעמא דלאכול
ולהקטיר. Ta'ama d'le'echol u'lehaktir. So the reason they don't combine is because
as I said they're separate acts, it's a plan to eat and
a plan to burn. הא לאכול ולאכול, Ha le'echol u'le'echol, if it
was a plan to eat and eat but the eating was the
eating of the of the קומץ, komets, meaning when you shift from
eating the שיריים shiurayim to burning the קומץ komets you've actually shifted
two things, the activity, the burning, and the object, the object is
the קומץ. komets. So what you actually did is you changed two
variables, right, maybe you weren't aware that you were changing the other
one, you changed two variables. It's like whenever we're driving in the
car and it's raining all of a sudden it stops raining. You
assume it's because it stopped time-wise but maybe it stopped because you're
in a different place now. So anyway, you switched two variables but
we sort of weren't aware that we were also switching the we
were also switching the קומץ. komets. So גמרא Gemara says, well why
did you have to switch two variables? It would sound like a
lesser switch would combine. So if you were planning on eating the
שיריים shiurayim and eating the קומץ komets that would combine because it's
two eatings even though the קומץ komets is not something that you're
allowed to eat. So that's what they're inferring, which is not a
bad inference because you know why compare it to a radically different
case and not a case that's more similar? So טעמא דלאכול ולהקטיר.
Ta'ama d'le'echol u'lehaktir. The reason they don't combine is one is eating
and one is offering incense, not incense, excuse me, burning it on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
It's the word להקטיר. lehaktir. הא לאכול ולאכול דבר
שאין דרכו לאכול, Ha le'echol u'le'echol davar she'ein darko le'echol, but if
eating and eating even if one of them is eating something that's
not normally eaten, meaning one is eating a half כזית kezayit of
the of the שיריים shiurayim and a half כזית kezayit of the
קומץ, komets, מצטרף, mitztaref, it sounds like that would combine. והקתני רישא,
Ve'hakatni reisha, but didn't we talk and say in the beginning, meaning
the earlier משנה, mishna, not first משנה, mishna, לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול
להקטיר דבר שדרכו להקטיר, le'echol davar she'darko le'echol lehaktir davar she'darko lehaktir,
that you're only חייב chayav if you have a thought of eating
שיריים shiurayim or burning the קומץ? komets? But a thought of eating
eating the קומץ komets is not relevant.
So דבר שדרכו לאכול אין, davar she'darko le'echol in, only you're only
חייב chayav if you plan on eating something that's normally eaten, the
שיריים. shiurayim. שאין דרכו לאכול לא, She'ein darko le'echol lo, and if
it's something not normally eaten, not normally eaten, the קומץ, komets, it
doesn't combine. So why does this משנה mishna imply otherwise? Otherwise. So
גמרא Gemara
says מאן תנא, Man tanna, who would be the תנא tanna of
this משנה mishna that would suggest this idea that you could actually
combine two forms of eating? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי
ירמיה הא מני רבי אליעזר היא, Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah ha manni Rabbi
Eliezer hi, it's רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר מחשבין מאכילת אדם לאכילת
מזבח ומאכילת מזבח לאכילת אדם. de'amar mechashvin me'achilat adam le'achilat mizbe'ach u'me'achilat
mizbe'ach le'achilat adam. That says actually you can combine the thought of
a person eating with the consumption of the altar. That those are
two forms of consumption and they can combine. דתנן, Ditnan, we taught
in a משנה mishna coming up in a few דפים, dapim, הקומץ
את המנחה לאכול דבר שאין דרכו לאכול ולהקטיר דבר שאין דרכו להקטיר
כשר. Hakomets et haminchah le'echol davar she'ein darko le'echol lehaktir davar she'ein
darko lehaktir kasher. So first we repeat the line from the משנה
mishna yesterday that if you do the קמיצה kemitzah and you plan
on eating something not normally eaten, meaning eating the קומץ, komets, or
burning something not normally burnt, not normally burnt, burning the שיריים, shiurayim,
then it's not a פיגול pigul thought because it's on an object
that you don't normally do this action with. רבי אליעזר פוסל, Rabbi
Eliezer posel, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, that is invalid.
Maybe it's not פיגול, pigul, okay, but at least it is invalid
because if you have a thought of eating on the קומץ komets
or thought of burning on the שיריים, shiurayim, at least it's a
form of eating, it's not completely irrelevant, so it's not enough to
classic activity that makes it פיגול pigul but it's enough to make
it invalid. And maybe that's what's implicit in our משנה Mishnah as
well, that only an eating and a burning don't combine, but an
eating and an eating, even an eating of the קומץ, kometz, would
combine.
So you're saying the first part of this משנה Mishnah
is not רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and it's the חכמים Hakhamim and
the second one is רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? Of course it's a
little bit of a סתם. stam. Right, and yeah, exactly. You know,
it is bizarre. In the end the גמרא's Gemara going to reject
all of this. Okay? But for now, so you don't have to
worry too much, but for now we're dealing with the sense that
the implication of this משנה Mishnah is that eating the קומץ kometz
would be חייב chayav and would combine. Okay? So אביי אמר Abaye
amar no, אפילו תימא רבנן. afilu teima Rabbanan. It's even the Rabbis.
Your whole inference, your reading between the lines in this משנה Mishnah
is not justified. Why?
לא תימא... lo teima... I just lost my place... אמר... amar... I
need a bigger גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
אפילו תימא רבנן. afilu teima Rabbanan. לא תימא lo teima אכילה ואכילה
דבר שאין דרכו לאכילה. achilah ve-achilah davar she-ein darko leachilah. Don't say
the implication is if you're going to combine two eatings, eating of
the שיריים shirayim and an eating of the קומץ kometz even though
it's not normally eaten, that that would be enough to invalidate it.
That's not the right implication of the משנה. Mishnah. אלא אימא ela
eima here's the implication: אכילה ואכילה דבר שדרכו לאכילה. achilah ve-achilah davar
she-darko leachilah. Okay, so it's saying no no no, it's not saying
that you know eating and eating of the קומץ, kometz, eating of
שיריים shirayim and eating of קומץ kometz combine. It's telling you eating
of שיריים shirayim and eating of שיריים shirayim combined. So obviously, so
the גמרא's Gemara saying,
meaning
if I want to eat this on Tuesday and the other on
Wednesday?
Well let's see. ומאי קמשמע לן, umai kamashma lan, what's it telling
us? ההדיא קתני לה, ha heidya ktani lah, it's implicit in the,
it's explicit in the previous משנה: Mishnah: אכילה כזית בחוץ וכזית למחר
כזית למחר וכזית בחוץ כחצי זית בחוץ וכחצי זית למחר כחצי זית
למחר וכחצי זית בחוץ פסול ואין בו כרת. achilah kezayit bachutz ukezayit
lemachar, kezayit lemachar ukezayit bachutz, kechatzi zayit bachutz vechatzi zayit lemachar, kechatzi
zayit lemachar vechatzi zayit bachutz, pasul ve-ein bo kareth. So here actually
it is a חידוש chiddush in the previous משנה Mishnah because if
you have an intent to eat a half of a כזית kezayit
in the wrong time and a half in the wrong place, even
though they're different types of invalidity, one's wrong time and one's wrong
place, and each one by itself is only a half of a
כזית, kezayit, because they're two forms of eating, they at least combine
to invalidate. They don't combine to make it פיגול pigul because it
wasn't a plan of a whole כזית kezayit in the wrong time,
but they enough combine to invalidate. So we've already learned that two
eatings combine even if they're of a different type, even if they're
one is a wrong time and one is a wrong place. So
why would this משנה Mishnah have to be implying that הלכה? halachah?
Right, that's how they're different, you know because obviously if they're the
exact same type of eating there's no חידוש chiddush at all. Why
would it have to apply it, state it, imply it, excuse me,
if it was explicit in the previous משנה? Mishnah? So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says, top of י"ג עמוד א': yud gimmel
amud aleph: הא תו למה לי? ha tu lama li? So why
would I need it to imply that two types of eating combine
if it's explicit again, if it's explicit in the previous
משנה? Mishnah? ואי אכילה ואכילה דבר שאין דרכו לאכילה, ve-ee achilah ve-achilah
davar she-ein darko leachilah, if it's to tell us that you can
combine eating and eating, something that is not normally eaten, קמשמע לן
דמצטרף מרישא שמעת מינה. kamashma lan de-mitztaref me-reisha shmat minei. So we
already heard it, learned it out from the רישא. reisha. What does
that mean? Hold on a minute, let me just double check רש"י
Rashi for a minute. Right, that it does not combine. Meaning it's
the line is funny of מרישא שמעת מינה. me-reisha shmat minei. If
you see there's a whole גירסא girsah on the side that switches
the גירסא. girsah. By the way, if you want to look at
this tiny little תוספות Tosafos just to interrupt for a sec on
the bottom of י"ב עמוד ב', yud bet amud bet, אלא אימא
אכילה ואכילה דבר שאין דרכו
לאכילה.
ela eima achilah ve-achilah davar she-ein
darko leachilah.
תוספות Tosafos says שדרכו לאכילה, she-darko leachilah, and תוספות Tosafos says מכאן
ואילך כתובה בספרים בשיבוש וצריך להגיה כאן כמו שכתובה בסוף פרק כיצד
צולים. mikan ve-eilach ketuvah besefarim beshibbush, vetzarich lehagia kan kemo she-ketuvah besof
perek keitzad tzolim. Okay, so meaning the whole text that תוספות Tosafos
had was very corrupt and he said you gotta copy it over
from the גמרא Gemara in זבחים Zvachim where we basically had this
סוגיא. sugya. Once again an instance of how problematic the texts are
in קדשים. Kodashim. By the way, when we get to חולין Chullin
it's a lot better because חולין Chullin was really learned. Anyway, so
I'll read this the way רש"י Rashi explains it. So it can't
be telling you you combine two different types of eating that are
eating of the שיריים, shirayim, that's explicit in the previous משנה. Mishnah.
ואי אכילה ואכילה דבר שאין דרכו לאכילה, ve-ee achilah ve-achilah davar she-ein
darko leachilah, if it's to tell you you can combine eating of
a half כזית kezayit of שיריים shirayim with a half כזית kezayit
of the קומץ, kometz, קמשמע לן דמצטרף מרישא שמעת מינה. kamashma lan
de-mitztaref me-reisha shmat minei. You infer it from the רישא, reisha, which
רש"י Rashi says in a very unusual meaning of that phrase, you
see from the רישא reisha it's not true. Okay, we already said
that from the רישא reisha it's clear that הקטרה haktarah and אכילה
achilah do not combine. Right, that's why the גמרא Gemara rejected this.
So ואי אכילה לא? ve-ee achilah lo? But this isn't, this isn't
הקטרה haktarah though, this is אכילה achilah right?
You're eating
meaning eating something that's the קומץ, kometz, it's not normally eaten.
No, but it's not אכילה והקטרה, achilah ve-haktarah, it's אכילה ואכילה achilah
ve-achilah we've been saying up until now, to do the אכילה achilah
in the wrong time, half a כזית kezayit in the wrong time
and
then half a כזית, kezayit, רישא, reisha, רישא reisha was not this
משנה. Mishnah. The רישא reisha was the
previous. What do we have? Say take a step back. We're trying
to be מדייק medayek from this משנה Mishna that talked about two
shifts. It says you can't combine eating of the שיריים Shirayim with
burning of the קומץ. Kometz. Now that's two things, the activity and
the object. So the גמרא Gemara wants to be מדייק medayek that
it sounds like eating of the שיריים Shirayim and eating of the
קומץ Kometz do combine, which is the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. The problem is, although the גמרא Gemara didn't say it earlier,
the way רש''י Rashi is reading this גמרא Gemara says it now.
It says the previous משנה Mishna made explicit that eating of the
קומץ Kometz was not, you know, a thought of eating of the
קומץ Kometz would not make it into פיגול, Pigul, would not make
a problem. So it's pretty bizarre to think that the משנה Mishna
shifted radically at the end and became רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay,
it's all what sounds like it's all one big משנה. Mishna. So
now the גמרא Gemara is saying סלקי, selaki, what is the implication?
If the implication is that two different real types of eating of
the שיריים, Shirayim, one חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, one חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo combine, if that's the implication, that if it's two different types
of eating that they would combine, that's explicit in the רישא. Reisha.
If the implication is that eating of the שיריים Shirayim and eating
of the קומץ Kometz combine, then the רישא Reisha of the משנה
Mishna says explicitly that eating of the קומץ Kometz doesn't count. And
parenthetically we're saying and it's absurd to think that at this stage
all of a sudden it's becoming רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, so
what is happening here? אי לאכול ולהקטיר, i le'echol u'lehaktir, if it's
telling you that a thought of, meaning it's not telling you any
דיוק, diyuk, it's just telling you the straight הלכה halacha that eating
and burning don't combine, מדיוקא דרישא שמעת מינה. midiyuka de'reisha shamat mina.
We didn't even need the משנה Mishna to say that. I could
have figured it out from the רישא. Reisha. How could I figure
it out from the רישא? Reisha? דהשתא מה לאכול ולאכול דבר שאין
דרכו לאכול אמרת לא מצטרפי. de'hashta mah le'echol u'le'echol davar she'ein darko
le'echol amrat lo mitztarfei. If eating a שיריים Shirayim and eating the
קומץ Kometz don't combine, even though they're both eatings,
so לאכול ולהקטיר מבעיא? le'echol u'lehaktir mibaya? So when it's eating and
burning, when it's different activities, of course it wouldn't combine! So then
the גמרא Gemara says, and finally we deal away with all of
these דיוקים, diyukim, אין, in, yes, לאכול ולהקטיר איצטריכא. le'echol u'lehaktir itztricha.
It's, the גמרא Gemara is saying,
forget all your דיוקים. diyukim. Okay, it's coming to tell you the,
you know, what it's explicitly saying: that you don't combine eating with
burning. Now the גמרא Gemara says, but you know, if you can't
combine eating with eating if it's the קומץ, Kometz, certainly you can't
combine eating with burning. The גמרא Gemara says no, that's not so
obvious.
How do you see that, how do you see that לאכול ולאכול
דבר שאין דרכו לאכול? le'echol u'le'echol davar she'ein darko le'echol?
You know what, let me finish and then you'll ask questions. Okay.
So, let me finish this because we've got to finish this thought.
Okay. So it's telling you the פשט, pshat, that you don't combine
eating with burning. So the גמרא Gemara says, but obviously if you
don't combine eating with eating if it's the קומץ, Kometz, you don't
combine eating with burning of the קומץ. Kometz. But it says no,
you do need to tell me that. מבעיא. mibaya. אין לאכול ולהקטיר
איצטריכא. in le'echol u'lehaktir itztricha. You have to tell me those don't
combine. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I would have thought, התם
הוא דלאו כי אורחיה קמחשב, hatam hu delav ki orchiah kamachshev, that
eating and eating, the reason they don't combine when I plan on
eating the קומץ Kometz is eating of the קומץ Kometz is a
totally absurd and meaningless activity. So therefore it obviously, even though they're
both eating, the second eating counts for nothing, so it won't combine.
אבל הכא דבהאי כי אורחיה קמחשב ובהאי כי אורחיה קמחשב, aval hacha
de'be'hai ki orchiah kamachshev u've'hai ki orchiah kamachshev, each one is a
meaningful activity. I'm eating שיריים Shirayim and I am burning קומץ, Kometz,
although they're different activities, but maybe if each one by itself makes
sense and is meaningful, maybe they could combine to be one set
of activities with a כזית. kezayis. So I might think, אימא ליצטרפו,
eima litzterfu, maybe they'll combine. קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. So
in the end the גמרא Gemara basically said what we would have
thought, you know, it's like, don't, you know, don't start reading in
דיוקים. diyukim. You know, no, it's true. You know, if you were
not to burn
the קומץ, Kometz, you were to eat the קומץ, Kometz, it also
wouldn't combine. But that doesn't mean, that doesn't mean that that's not
something that then this is obvious, because actually burning the קומץ Kometz
might have more of a reason to combine than eating the קומץ,
Kometz, because burning the קומץ Kometz is a logical activity. Okay, so
what have we basically said to sum this up? We've said that
you're only חייב, chayav, bracketing רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that we'll see
later that combines eating and burning, you're only חייב chayav if you
plan on eating the שיריים Shirayim or burning the קומץ. Kometz. You
cannot combine, you cannot combine those two a half of a כזית
kezayis of each, even though those are meaningful activities in themselves, you
can't combine them. That's what our משנה Mishna is saying. Not only
that, if you plan on doing the wrong activity with the particular
object, burning the שיריים Shirayim or eating the קומץ, Kometz, then there
would be, that would count for nothing either. Okay, so if you
plan on doing the wrong activity with the object it counts for
nothing. If you plan on doing the right activity it counts, but
you cannot combine two separate activities, the eating of the, of the
שיריים Shirayim and the burning of the קומץ. Kometz. Okay, so that's
the פשט pshat and the דיוקים diyukim are not necessarily. The קומץ
Kometz then that there would be that would count for nothing either.
Okay, so if you plan on doing the wrong activity with the
object that counts for nothing either. Okay, so if you plan on
doing the wrong activity with the object it counts for nothing. If
you plan on doing the right activity it counts, but you cannot
combine two separate activities, the eating of the שיריים Shi'rayim and the
burning of the קומץ. Kometz. Okay, so that's the פשט P'shat and
the דיוקים Diyukim are not necessary. הדרן עלך כל המנחות. Hadran alach
kol haminachot.
That ends this פרק. Perek. Now, we have been given the blessing
of a very short דף Daf here. Normally it's cause of a
large תוספות. Tosfos. Here we've got this thing which looks like a
large רש"י, Rashi, but it isn't. And if you look at the
beginning of it, like right after the הדרן עלך Hadran alach in
the רש"י, Rashi, it says: דקדוק שפירשו הרב מאיר והרב שמואל בנו
ז"ל. Dikduk sheperishu Harav Meir veHarav Shmuel beno zal.
So who is רב מאיר Rav Meir and רב שמואל בנו? Rav
Shmuel beno? What is ז"ל? zal? זכר זכרונו לחיי העולם הבא. Zecher
zichrono lachayei ha'olam haba. Okay, so I should say זכר צדיק לברכה.
Zecher tzadik livracha.
Yeah,
it's a form of זצ"ל. zatzal. Okay, so who are they? Does
anybody know? Who's רב שמואל בר רב מאיר? Rav Shmuel bar Rav
Meir? That's the רשב"ם, Rashbam, right? רש"י's Rashi's grandson. גוטן טאג. Guten
tag. רבנו תם's Rabbeinu Tam's brother. People think they're cousins, they're brothers.
He's רבנו תם's Rabbeinu Tam's older brother. So this was רש"י's Rashi's
son and—or son-in-law I should say—and the רשב"ם, Rashbam, his grandson. רב
מאיר Rav Meir is the son-in-law. Right. And if you look at
the bottom, right before it starts with הקומץ, Hakometz, עד כאן הדקדוק
שפירש רב שמואל ואביו הרב מאיר. Ad kan hadikduk sheperish Rav Shmuel
veaviv Harav Meir.
So why did they insert this? Cause this basically explains the whole
סוגיא Sugya we did yesterday. Remember the whole סוגיא Sugya we did
yesterday, like we couldn't make any sense out of this, how רבא
Rava was saying that since רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya didn't say כזית,
Kezayis, it means he's talking about שיריים Shi'rayim and it was this
very bizarre proof, you know, whatever. So he re-explains the סוגיא, Sugya,
tries to make it make more sense. It helps a little. I'm
not going to go through what he says. He really only changes
one little nuance which helps a little bit about how רבא Rava
got it from the text. But the editor maybe had this separate
piece and he included it. It's quite fascinating that it's a standalone
explanation of the רשב"ם Rashbam on the previous סוגיא. Sugya. Okay, but
it certainly makes our דף Daf today quite short.
But he didn't put it with the תוספות, Tosfos, he put it
with the רש"י.
Rashi. He put it with the רש"י Rashi cause it is more—it's
a commentary the same way the רשב"ם Rashbam in בבא בתרא, Bava
Basra, you know, is a—look, when you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam,
you see the greatness of רש"י, Rashi, cause you know, it takes
the רשב"ם Rashbam five times as many words to say what—of course
you have to read רש"י Rashi more closely, you know, but רש"י
Rashi certainly had the gift of being terse. Sometimes the רשב"ם Rashbam
introduces some of the types of תוספות-type Tosafos of questions: oh, what
about this סוגיא, Sugya, what about that סוגיא? Sugya? But not always.
In this entire commentary, it's straight commentary of the גמרא, Gemara, it's
no types of critical questions, and it still takes him, you know,
a lot more space than רש"י. Rashi. Okay, so now we're—did you
have any final questions about the previous סוגיא Sugya
before we read the משנה? Mishna? Well, I didn't, but then I
looked in the רש"י Rashi and he explained how that happened.
Okay, good. Now we're going to start, of course, even though we
now shift פרק, Perek, as you remember from זבחים, Zevachim, once we
get into פיגול, Pigul, we stay with it for a while. So
we're going to continue this פרק Perek which has a lot to
do with פיגול Pigul of the מנחות. Minachos. So let's take a
look. הקומץ את המנחה Hakometz es hamincha לאכול שיריה או להקטיר קומצה
למחר. le'echol shireha o lehaktir kumtza lemachar. So you do the קמיצה
Kmitza of the מנחה Mincha to eat the remainder tomorrow or to
burn the קומץ Kometz tomorrow. Classic פיגול Pigul thought. We actually said
this in the previous משנה. Mishna. מודה רבי יוסי בזה שהוא פיגול.
Modeh Rabbi Yose b'zeh shehu pigul. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would
agree that this is פיגול. Pigul. This is like bizarre: who's רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose and why would I think he would disagree? So
actually, it's saying that because it's about to introduce you to an
opinion of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and it wants to make it
clear from the outset—it's quite fascinating—that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose agrees to
the basic idea of פיגול, Pigul, but he's going to argue in
a case you're about to see. So let's see what that case
is.
בזה שהוא פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. B'zeh shehu pigul vechayavin alav kares.
Now, how about the following case? להקטיר לבונה למחר. Lehaktir levona lemachar.
Let's say you are taking the קומץ Kometz with the intent to
burn the לבונה Levona tomorrow. So you're not—you're not going to eat
the שיריים Shi'rayim at the wrong time or burn the קומץ Kometz
at the wrong time, you're going to burn the לבונה Levona at
the wrong time. רבי יוסי אומר פסול ואין בו כרת. Rabbi Yose
omer pasul ve'ein bo kares. It's invalid because it's a thought of
wrong time, but there's no כרת. Kares. It's not פיגול. Pigul. וחכמים
אומרים פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. Vachachamim omrim pigul vechayavin alav kares. No,
it is פיגול. Pigul. It's something about the מנחה Mincha that you're
going to do at the wrong time. אמרו לו, Amru lo, so
they said to רבי יוסי: Rabbi Yose: מה שינה זה מן הזבח?
Mah shina zeh min hazevach? How is this different than an animal
sacrifice? Meaning, an animal sacrifice you don't—you do more than just the
blood on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. What do you do on the מזבח?
Mizbe'ach? You burn the חלב, Cheilev, the fat. So if I do
the זריקת הדם, Zrikas hadam, it's not only about when I'm going
to eat the meat, I could have a פיגול Pigul thought about
the blood, about eating the meat, or about burning the fat. So
why can't here I have a פיגול Pigul thought about burning the
קומץ, Kometz, eating the שיריים, Shi'rayim, or burning the לבונה? Levona? How
is it any different than an animal sacrifice? אמר להן, Amar lahen,
here is a difference: שהזבח דמו ובשרו ואימוריו. Shehazevach damo uvesaro veimurav.
The blood, the meat, and the
entrails—אחד—is Echad all one, one unit. הלבונה אינה מן המנחה. Halevona eina
min hamincha. The לבונה Levona is not part of the מנחה. Mincha.
So it's true, I agree to the basic idea of פיגול, Pigul,
if you plan on eating the שיריים Shi'rayim or burning the קומץ
Kometz at the wrong time it's פיגול, Pigul, but this is external
to the מנחה. Mincha. So it sounds like here that his issue
is that you cannot create פיגול Pigul by having a thought about
something that's a different object. Okay, so even though it's something that
has to be brought with the מנחה, Mincha, and actually it was
physically placed on top of the מנחה, Mincha, but conceptually the way
the תורה Torah defines it is you place the לבונה Levona על
המנחה. al hamincha. So even though it's physically in the same כלי,
Kli, it's a different thing that's riding on top, so therefore... Or
you cannot have a, it would not be a פגול pigul thought
to plan on doing something wrong with a related object which is
not defined as the same object. That seems to be what he's
saying. The גמרא Gemara is going to reinterpret it. But there would
be other implications of this. For example, how about a שלמים Shlamim
where you bring bread with the animal? Right? And these issues will
sort of come up. Let's say I שחט shecht the שלמים Shlamim
with the דעת da'as to eat a כזית k'zayis of the bread
at the wrong time. Okay? So yes, it comes, and it's, you
know, it's part of the, you know, sacrifice בגדר, begeder, but it's
not part of the object that I'm right now doing the עבודה
avoda with. So that, it seems that that's what he's saying, that
that might invalidate, but פגול pigul have to be relating to the
object itself. What?
Or נסכים, Nesachim, if I had a פגול pigul thought about the
נסכים, Nesachim, exactly. So let's take a look how the גמרא Gemara
frames it, because it seems like his position is quite clear, but
the גמרא Gemara is going to frame it differently. So, למה לי
למתני מודה רבי יוסי בזו, lama li lemisni modeh Reb Yose bezo,
why did it have to, why does the משנה mishna have to
start, says the גמרא, Gemara, with this case רבי יוסי Reb Yose
agrees with? משום דקבעי למתני סיפא, mishum deka'bai lemisni seifa, because the
end of the משנה, mishna, it's going to say, להקטיר לבונתה למחר
רבי יוסי אומר פסול ואין בו כרת. lehakteer levontoh lemachar Reb Yose
omer pasul ve'ein bo kareis. So רבי יוסי Reb Yose says that
if you have a thought about the לבונה, levona, it does not
make פגול. pigul. It's invalid, but it doesn't make פגול. pigul. מהו
דתימא, mahu detema, I might have thought, טעמא דרבי יוסי, ta'ama de'Reb
Yose, the reasoning of רבי יוסי, Reb Yose, is משום דקסבר אין
מפגלין בחצי מתיר, mishum de'kasavar ein mepaglin be'chatzi matir, that's our friend.
You don't create פגול pigul with half of a מתיר. matir. Now
this is an imprecise use of this phrase, which תוספות Tosafos already
says. מפגלין בחצי מתיר mepaglin be'chatzi matir means that if there are
two things that need to be done to make the קרבן korban
valid, the question is, can the פגול pigul thought be effective when
I only have it on one of them? So a classic example
actually would be the קטורת, Ketores, but the other side of the
equation. If I have my פגול pigul thought when I'm taking the
קומץ, kometz, actually here I didn't mean קטורת, Ketores, I meant לבונה,
levona, but it was closer.
Okay, the לבונה. levona. If I am taking my קומץ kometz and
planning on eating, I don't know, the שריים shirayim at the wrong
time, that's, you could say that's a חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, because
the מנחה mincha does not become valid just from what I'm going
to do by the קומץ, kometz, it actually also becomes valid because
of what I'm going to do by the לבונה. levona. So maybe
I have to have my פגול pigul thought for both of them.
That's a question of מפגלין בחצי מתיר. mepaglin be'chatzi matir. We will
see in the גמרא Gemara that maybe not, maybe the act of
the לבונה, levona, although it's necessary, is seen as somewhat secondary. Okay,
but that's the issue of מפגלין בחצי מתיר. mepaglin be'chatzi matir. If
I have my thought in one of the two acts that are
needed to make it valid. So the, for example, another case the
גמרא Gemara applies it to is during the שחיטה. shechita. If the
act of שחיטה shechita is defined as both cutting the trachea and
the esophagus, when I only cut one of them, it's only half
of the act. It's חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. Is that enough of
a פגול pigul or do I have to cut both? This is
not חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. This is not you're having the thought
only during part of the activity and not the whole activity. Here
you're having the thought during the whole activity but it's only about
half of what you are going to burn. Meaning the object of
the thought, not the activity you're doing. Your object of your thought
here is about the קומץ kometz and it's not about the לבונה.
levona. So the גמרא Gemara is saying like this: I might have
thought that you know why רבי יוסי Reb Yose says you don't
make פגול pigul when you think just about the לבונה, levona, because
maybe he thinks that you have to think about both objects that
are burnt. Since they're both burnt they both make the קרבן korban
כשר, kosher, right? So it's the לבונה levona and the קומץ, kometz,
maybe you have to think about both objects. Now we had that
yesterday, Michael was referring to the סיפא seifa where רבי אלעזר. Reb
Elazar. רבי אלעזר Reb Elazar says you're not חייב chayav by העלאת
חוץ ha'alas chutz until you burn both the קומץ kometz and the
לבונה. levona. You have to do the full thing, so רבי אלעזר
Reb Elazar would also say you're not חייב chayav for פגול pigul
unless you're thinking about both the קומץ kometz and the לבונה. levona.
I was looking at the רבי יוסי. Reb Yose.
What? That was רבי אלעזר. Reb Elazar.
No, but where did רבי יוסי Reb Yose come in?
It was in the משנה, mishna, you were out today.
No, but where מודה רבי יוסי, modeh Reb Yose, did we have
it before? No. So why are we saying,
because read the whole משנה, mishna, the end of the משנה, mishna,
okay? You can't ask questions if you come in the middle of
class.
Alright, anyway,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. I would have thought
רבי יוסי's Reb Yose position is you have to think about both
the קומץ kometz and the לבונה levona because they work together, sort
of like the רבי אלעזר Reb Elazar we had before. And then
if you thought just about the קומץ, kometz, you also would not
make פגול. pigul. So I might have thought that that's the case.
ואפילו רישא נמי, ve'afilu reisha nami, and therefore you would argue even
in the first half, even by just having a thought about the
קומץ, kometz, קא משמע לן דבהא מודה, kamashma lan de'beha modeh, that
that he agrees, okay? That it has nothing to do with you
have to think about both objects. It has to do specifically about
the problem of the לבונה. levona. Alright, now again, the point is
don't get, although the גמרא Gemara was imprecise, don't get it confused.
This is not really a case of חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. חצי
מתיר chatzi matir is you're having the thought during part of the
activity and not the full activity. This is a case where you're
thinking about, you're thinking as the object of your thought one of
the two things. Other than רבי אלעזר Reb Elazar before, that we
never said was a problem. We've always assumed thinking about the קומץ
kometz is enough. But now we're going to turn to the question
about what is the problem with the לבונה? levona? Let's take a
look. להקטיר לבונתה למחר רבי יוסי אומר פסול ואין בו כרת. lehakteer
levontoh lemachar Reb Yose omer pasul ve'ein bo kareis. To burn the
לבונה Levona tomorrow, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says you do not make
פיגול. Pigul. It is invalid, but you do not make פיגול Pigul
when it's only a thought about the לבונה. Levona. So we said
simple read of the משנה Mishna because it's not part of the
same object that you're doing the קמיצה Kemitzah to. Let's see how
the גמרא Gemara explains it. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, אומר
היה רבי יוסי, Omer haya Rabbi Yossi, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi used
to say, meaning the explanation of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is, it's
actually interesting because אומר היה רבי יוסי Omer haya Rabbi Yossi makes
it sound like he really had a tradition that this is what
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi used to say, but he's really speculating on
רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi's reasoning. If you look at רש"י Rashi two
lines down, אומר היה רבי יוסי, Omer haya Rabbi Yossi, כלומר היינו
טעמא דרבי יוסי. Klomar hainu ta'ama de-Rabbi Yossi. Okay, so it's not
like he has a tradition that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi really said
this. It's like saying, this is what it means. Okay, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi is saying, here's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is saying:
אין מתיר מפגל את המתיר. Ein matir mefagel es ha-matir. Okay, it's
not because the לבונה Levona is separate from the object of the
מנחה, Mincha, it's because you only have a פיגול Pigul thought when
you're dealing with the מתיר, Matir, that your פיגול Pigul thought is
only when you're dealing with the object that's going to make the
קרבן Korban valid, either when you're dealing with the דם Dam by
a קרבן Korban or with the קומץ. Kometz. That's when your פיגול
Pigul thought is meaningful. You don't have a פיגול Pigul thought, for
example, when you're dealing with burning the אימורים. Emurim. It's only when
you're dealing with the מתיר. Matir. Now, normally what is my פיגול
Pigul thought about? Let's take the קרבן Korban case. I'm dealing with
the דם. Dam. I can have a פיגול Pigul thought about eating
the meat. Well, that's not a מתיר. Matir. I can have the
פיגול Pigul thought about burning the אימורים Emurim at the wrong time.
That's not a מתיר. Matir. I also can have a פיגול Pigul
thought about being זורק הדם Zorek ha-dam at the wrong time, but
that's about itself. So what they're saying is רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi's
point is that you can't have a פיגול Pigul thought about another
מתיר Matir other than itself. And because the לבונה Levona is another
מתיר, Matir, so not because the לבונה Levona is a physically separate
object, even if it was physically the same object, because it's a
different מתיר, Matir, your thought of פיגול Pigul only works on either
what is becoming allowed or the thing itself. Not another thing which
functions as a מתיר. Matir. Okay, which in a certain way makes
sense because the whole idea is by taking this דם, Dam, let's
say, then this דם Dam is going to validate, it's going to
affect the status of the meat and the אימורים. Emurim. So my
thought while I'm taking this דם Dam could be is relevant to
the things that this דם Dam will affect. This דם Dam will
also, is and also because I'm taking the דם, Dam, my thought
is relevant to the דם Dam itself. Okay, but it's not relevant
to some other thing that's going to have an impact on, you
know, on the meat, if that were to exist. So by the
קומץ, Kometz, the קומץ Kometz is relevant to the שיריים. Shirayim. It
impacts the status of the שיריים. Shirayim. I'm taking the קומץ, Kometz,
I can have a thought about the קומץ. Kometz. But the קומץ
Kometz does not have, there's no dependency relationship between the לבונה Levona
and the קומץ. Kometz. The לבונה Levona stands by itself. And therefore
my act during taking the קומץ Kometz cannot be פיגול Pigul on
the לבונה. Levona. So whether it's not פשט Pshat necessarily in the
משנה, Mishna, but there's a logic, there's a very good logic to
it.
And the reason why he's saying that if I מפיגל Mefagel the
קומץ Kometz tomorrow, even though taking the קומץ Kometz is מתיר Matir
it, because
it's the thing itself I'm doing the act to. So I can
have my thought about the thing itself. I can have my thought
about the things that are dependent on this object, right, which is
the שיריים Shirayim or the meat and the אימורים Emurim in a
case, in an animal case. But I can't have my thought on
some other thing which doesn't have a dependency relationship with the קומץ
Kometz that I'm taking.
No, my question more was that, you know, when you introduce something,
wouldn't you usually say, even the person we're going to talk about
later is going to agree.
Yeah, I know, I know, I understand. But it seems anyway it
probably was a later gloss on the, edit on the משנה Mishna
or something. I don't know. All right, so let's take a look.
This is how ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is explaining it. וכן אתה
אומר, Ve-chein ata omer, and now we're going to apply this principle
to another case. בשני בזיכי לבונה של לחם הפנים, Bi-shnei bezichei levona
shel lechem ha-panim, that you had those two, you know, spoons or
bowls of לבונה Levona for the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, שאין מתיר
מפגל את המתיר. She-ein matir mefagel es ha-matir. That if you're burning
one of the bowls, right, of this frankincense and you had a
thought about, oh, I'm going to burn the other bowl of frankincense
tomorrow, that is not פיגול. Pigul. Now, here, what, right here they're
the same physical object. But they are seen as two separate activities.
It's not just seen as a lump of לבונה, Levona, you know,
as divided into two things. They're seen as two separate things and
each act, the combined two activities are מתיר. Matir. So the bread
is dependent on the לבונה. Levona. But one of the bowls of
לבונה Levona is not dependent on the other. So when I do
an activity with one bowl, it does not affect the status or
not enough to make it פיגול Pigul of the other bowl. Okay?
Like if you mess up the first bowl then you would still
do the second bowl?
No, you need both to make the קרבן Korban valid. Like if
you had a chart, right, it would be like this. You know,
you'd have like A and B make the, make the קרבן, Korban,
like the לבונה Levona and the, and the קומץ Kometz make the
שיריים מותר. Shirayim mutar. Or this bowl and this bowl make the
לחם הפנים מותר. Lechem HaPanim mutar. So this is dependent on this
and it's dependent on this. So when you're doing something with this
or with this, you can affect the status of this. But these
two are not dependent on one another. Doing both of them makes
this good, right? But, but a thought about this doesn't affect that
because they're not dependent on each other. I'm sorry, what?
Just theoretically, I could understand that too. doing it but in practicality
with this קרבן korban *korban* if you ruin one what's it called
בזיך *bazich* yeah then
you can't use the other one. Correct. So then they are dependent.
Yeah, meaning they stop being purposeful, but it's that's true. I mean,
when one gets ruined, the whole קרבן korban *korban* you know becomes
purposeless. That's true, but it's not you know it's not like doing
this correctly impacts the status of this. So that's sort of the
distinction. But you're right, doing it incorrectly means you have to throw
it all out. All right. Right.
Right. The other one too.
Right. Right. That right. You know that's you know what's being asked,
but that's not considered depend -- I mean, the way I'm framing
it, I'm using different language than the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. The way
אין מתיר matir *ein matir* מפקע מתיר matir *mapka matir*, but the
logic I think has to do with this issue of dependency.
What's the word מתיר matir. *matir*?
Like, what does מתיר matir *matir* -- מתיר *Matir* means the thing
which makes the קרבן korban. *korban* permissible. So if I זורק *zorek*
the דם dam *dam*, I can eat the meat. Or if I
זורק *zorek* the דם *dam*, I can burn the אימורים *imurim* on
the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*, even though they're not permissible for me to
eat, but they become now allowed to be do something now, the
next stage with it. Right? So bringing this does not allow this
to be brought because I could switch the order. Okay, that's the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* is actually going to say that in a minute.
The order doesn't matter. If the order mattered, if you had to
do the קומץ kometz *kometz* before the לבונה levonah. *levonah*, then the
קומץ kometz. *kometz* would be מתיר *matir* the לבונה levonah *levonah*, and
then actually you would be able to make פיגול pigul *pigul*. Okay?
But you can't bring the לבונה levonah. *levonah* first. Exactly. So since
order doesn't matter, there's no dependency of one on the other. Exactly.
They're not מתיר *matir*.
You can't bring לבונה levonah *levonah* first.
Yeah, we're about to say that. Okay. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara*
says like this.
So מהו דתימא *mahu deteima*... okay, so the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says
מאי חזית דאמרת *mai chazit de'amrat*, why did he have to say
and you can say the same you would say the same thing
by the two בזיכין bazichin *bezichin*?
I would think it wouldn't be.
Well, exactly. That's what the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says. No, מהו דתימא
*mahu deteima* because I could have thought רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi
Yose* was something totally different. טעמא דרבי יוסי בלבונה *Ta'ama deRabbi Yose
belevonah*, the reason רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi Yose* says there's not
a פיגול pigul *pigul* by לבונה levonah, *levonah*, משום דלאו מינא דמנחה
היא *mishum delav mina demincha hi*, because it's not the same object
as the מנחה mincha *mincha*. And it's a special דין *din* about
the לבונה levonah *levonah* being conceptually distinct from the מנחה mincha. *mincha*.
אבל בשני בזיכי לבונה bazichei levona. דמינא דהדדי נינהו *Aval bishnei bezichei
levonah demina dehadadi ninhu*, the two you know cups or spoons of
the frankincense by the לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim* that they're all the
same object. I mean you know again they're like being separate bowls,
but at least conceptually are much more one object. So therefore in
that case, אימא מפקגי להדדי *eima mapgei lahadadi*, maybe it creates פיגול
pigul *pigul*. קא משמע לן *Ka mashma lan* that it doesn't. Meaning
basically I would have thought פשטא דמתניתין *peshata dematnitin* that it's a
unique problem with לבונה levonah *levonah* because it's a physically different object
and it's conceptually different, and maybe I wouldn't have applied it to
two בזיכי לבונה bazichei levona. *bezichei levonah* which are essentially all לבונה
levonah *levonah*. Maybe there רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi's *Rabbi Yose* would have
created פיגול pigul *pigul*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is now going
to say, Oh, but you know what? Actually it does sound that
way from the משנה mishna *Mishnah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
let's take a look. ומי מצית אמרת *Umi matzit amrat*, how could
you say דטעמא דרבי יוסי בלבונה לאו משום דלאו מינא דמנחה היא
*deta'ama deRabbi Yose belevonah lav mishum delav mina demincha hi*? How could
you say that it's not because they're not the same object? That
actually is what the משנה mishna *Mishnah* says. והקתני סיפא *Vehakatani seifa*,
the end of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* says, אמרו לו *amru lo*,
they said to him, מה שינתה... מה
שינתה מן הזבח *mah shintah min hazevach*, how is it different than
you know a thought relating to the אימורים *imurim* by a animal
sacrifice? אמר להם *Amar lahem*, הזבח דמו ובשרו ואימוריו אחד *hazevach damo
uvesaro ve'imurav echad*, there it's all one, the blood and the meat
and the entrails. והלבונה אינה מינא דמנחה *Vehalevonah einah mina demincha*, and
the לבונה levonah *levonah* is not the same thing as the מנחה
mincha. *mincha*. So he's not saying because the לבונה levonah *levonah* is
a מתיר *matir*. He's saying because it's somehow a different type of
an object. So you see that is his reason. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says no no no that's not what it means. מאי
אינה מינא דמנחה *Mai einah mina demincha*, what does it mean it's
not of one with the מנחה mincha, *mincha*? It means אינה בעיכוב
מנחה mincha *einah be'ikuv mincha*. It's not something that is being held
back by the מנחה mincha, *mincha*. דלאו כהיכא דמעכב להו קומץ kometz,
לשיריים *Delav kehicha dema'akev lehu kometz leshirayim*, it does not operate the
same way the קומץ kometz *kometz* holds back the שיריים *shirayim*, the
remnant. So it's not dependent. Meaning it's not like the
מנחה mincha, *mincha*. The מנחה mincha. *mincha* is dependent on the bringing
of the קומץ kometz *kometz* to make it valid. This is not
like the מנחה mincha, *mincha*. This acts independently of it. Which now
that we read this we realize, you know, that's actually not a
bad read. Okay. Well no, before your question we're going to finish
the thought. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אינה בעיכוב מנחה
mincha, *einah be'ikuv mincha*, it's not held back like the מנחה mincha.
*mincha* is held back. דלאו כהיכא דמעכב להו קומץ kometz לשיריים *Delav
kehicha dema'akev lehu kometz leshirayim*, it's not like the same way the
קומץ kometz, *kometz* holds back the remnant. דכמה דלא מתקטר קומץ kometz
לא lo, מיתכלו שיריים *Dechama dela mitkatar kometz la mitchalu shirayim*, so
here you go exactly explaining what the idea of מתיר *matir* is,
that until you burn the קומץ kometz *kometz*, the שיריים *shirayim* can't
be eaten. So the קומץ kometz. *kometz* is a מתיר *matir* for
the שיריים *shirayim* and they're dependent on the שיריים *shirayim*. Don't say
הכי נמי מעכב לה ללבונה *hachi nami ma'akev lah lalevonah*, that the
קומץ kometz. *kometz* holds back the לבונה levonah. *levonah* from being brought.
Not true. אלא אי בעי האי מקטר ברישא *Ela i bei hai
maktar bereisha*, if he wants he burns this first. אי בעי האי
מקטיר Maktir, ברישא, אי בעי האי מקטיר ברישא. If you want, you
can burn the קומץ kometz first. If you want, you can burn
the לבונה. levonah.
Or not at all?
So, no, not not at all. You need to burn it to
make the מנחה mincha valid, but it's exactly like I said. You
have two separate things, not dependent on each other. Each one can
go first. This one does absolutely nothing for this, but combined they
help the מנחה. mincha So your thought on this can make פיגול
pigul on itself and on the מנחה. minchah. Your thought on that
can do פיגול pigul on itself and on the מנחה, minchah? but
your thought on one cannot affect the other because there is no
dependent relationship of one to the other. So לאו מינא דמנחה lav
mina demincha does not just mean it's physically different and it's a
different object. It means that it doesn't... it's not dependent on... it's
not like the מנחה minchah that it's dependent on the קומץ. komeitz
Yes, Michael.
So my question is, if you just look at this whole thing,
you know, it does mention the word חוק chok over there, but
you know, it's at the very end so I just wonder how
the גמרא Gemara דרשנס darshens it. Whenever you have חוק, chok, it's
like everything in it has to be this way and you can't,
like, do this first, you can't do this second.
Of whether the order matters?
Yeah, doesn't matter? Because חוק chok is like the עיכוב. ikuv. You
have to do it.
I understand, but it didn't say חוק chok about the order, it
just said חוק chok in sort of a very generic sense. Look,
as you already know, Michael, the גמרא Gemara decides when and how
broadly or narrowly to define these terms. So I'm not going to
let that bother me. Okay, let's keep on going.
Is the גמרא Gemara going to address it?
I'll have to see. I don't remember. Okay, so let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says ורבנן, verabanan, what would the rabbis
say? כי אמרינן אין מתיר מפגל את המתיר, ki amrinan ein matir
mefagel et hamatir, I might agree that normally we would say one
מתיר does not create פיגול pigul, on the other because we're going
to see in a משנה Mishna in a couple of דפים, dappim,
they're going to give a case about the two lambs that are
brought with the שתי הלחם shtei halechem on... on שבועות. Shavuot. And
those are שלמים shlamim lambs, the only example of שלמי ציבור. shlamei
tzibur. We bring those two lambs and they allow the bread to
be eaten. So in an ironic way, because normally you don't think
about the קרבן korban as being מתיר of the bread, but anyway,
here
the focus is on the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and bringing the
קרבן korban is מתיר. So if I bring one lamb and I'm
planning on, you know, eating the other lamb in the wrong place,
right? In this case of the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, would that
be a פיגול pigul thought? That's an idea of like מתיר מפגל
את המתיר. matir mefagel et hamatir. So there we say the rabbis
might agree, but it's not the same as here. Let's take a
look. הני מילי, hani mili, when do they say אין מתיר מפגל
את המתיר? ein matir mefagel et hamatir? הני מילי היכא דלא אקבו
בחד מנא, hani mili heicha dela ikvu behad mana, where they're not
all put into one vessel, meaning that they're not... that they're conceptually
distinct or physically and conceptually. אבל הכא דאקבו בחד מנא, aval hacha
deikvu behad mana, here where you do wind up putting the לבונה
levonah. in the same vessel as the מנחה, minchah, you lay it
on top of the מנחה, minchah כחד דמי, kechad dami, it's like
one, which really means they totally agree in principle, they just disagree
in applying it to the case of the לבונה. levonah, They say
when you have these two lambs of שבועות, Shavuot, that if a
פיגול pigul. thought from one lamb to the other doesn't work because
it's the same thing, these two lambs can be brought in either
order and they both operate to make the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
permissible. So this has nothing to do with that and therefore you
cannot have a פיגול pigul thought from one lamb to the other.
Fine. That they agree. They agree in principle. But they say the
לבונה levonah is conceptually part of the מנחה. You put it in
the same כלי kli as the מנחה, you sanctify it with the
מנחה, so it is not considered a distinct thing. And therefore when
you do something with the קומץ, komeitz it can, although הלכתית halachitit
it doesn't change the status of the לבונה, levonah a thought about
the קומץ komeitz is relevant to the לבונה levonah, because conceptually it's
one with the מנחה. Okay, so that makes a lot of sense.
So now we have a very clear understanding. They agree in principle
and the question is what? And it would be פיגול, pigul correct.
And that's what the משנה mishna. says, that the rabbis say, right,
חכמים אומרים hachamim omrim that a פיגול pigul thought on the קומץ
komets on the לבונה levonah. makes פיגול.
pigul So if I want to eat, if I want to do
חצי קומץ מן הלבונה למחר וחצי כזית מן הקומץ,
chatzi kometz min halevonah lemachar vechatzi kezayit
min hakometz, would they be
מצטרף? mitztaref?
I don't know, I mean, I think actually some of that is
coming up so I can't give you a full answer right now.
But that's... but you're right. Logically if we're emphasizing that it's sort
of seen as
one, then that would be, you know, a pretty logical conclusion on
that. We'll have to see how that plays out. Okay, so let's
take a look now where the גמרא Gemara. goes with it. אמר
רבי ינאי: amar rabbi yanai: ליקוט לבונה בזר פסול. likut levonah bezar
pasul. Now
we... it seems like we're on a different... on a tangent, but
we will see how it ties in. He says if a non-כהן
kohen does,
gathers the לבונה levonah. off of the מנחה and then gives it
to the כהן. kohen. So the כהן kohen is going to go
and take the לבונה levonah and put it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
but it's a non-כהן kohen who picked it off the surface of
the מנחה and gave it to the כהן. kohen. So to one
degree the question could be, the תורה Torah never describes being קומץ
komets or taking the לבונה levonah off. It just says you burn
the לבונה. levonah Is there conceptually an עבודה avodah of ליקוט לבונה
likut levonah the same way there's an עבודה avodah of קמיצה? kemitza?
So he is saying there is an עבודה avodah called ליקוט לבונה.
likut levonah. It has to be done, but it's an עבודה. avodah.
Therefore even a non-כהן Kohen can do it. Okay, ליקוט לבונה בזר
פסול. likut levonah bezar pasul. I'm sorry. So he says it is
פסול. pasul. The גמרא Gemara, is going to challenge it, I'm sorry.
So he says it is פסול. pasul. Now presumably that could be
for the reason that he says maybe that's similar to the קמיצה.
kmitzah. Because
מקמיצה ואילך קמיצות כהן, mikmitzah ve'elech kmitzot kohen, you say, is that
what he's saying? No, I'm saying because it parallels. There's the removing
of the קמיצה, kmitzah, there's the removing of the לבונה. levonah, The
only difference is the תורה Torah never describes this as an act.
It just says it should be מקטיר לבונה. maktir levonah. It doesn't
tell you the act, right, how you get it off the מנחה.
Therefore אין עונש מן הדין. ein onesh min hadin.
We're not talking about an עונש. onesh. We're talking about...
No, but
if a זר zar did it, though, he wouldn't be...
No, first of all, it's not an עבודה תמה avodah tama and
all those things, okay? So no. Okay, so anyway, let's take a
look.
Okay, so anyway he says it's פסול. pasul. It is invalid. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אמר רב ירמיה, Amar Rav Yirmiyah,
so רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah says different than I would have suggested,
but mine will come up at the end. משום הולכה נגעו בה.
Mishum holacha nag'u bah. It's a type of הולכה, holacha, of conveying
it to the מזבח, mizbe'ach. and הולכה holacha we know is an
עבודה avodah and presumably even by the קטורת. ketoret. Now by the
לבונה. levonah So that was not a mistake now for קומץ, komets
it was a mistake for לבונה, levonah. I can go either way
with my קטורת. ketoret. Okay, anyway, so what does that mean? קסבר
הולכה שלא ברגל שמה הולכה. Kasavar holacha shelo beregel shemah holacha. Moving,
conveying, even without walking is a form of conveyance, is the עבודה
avodah of הולכה. holacha. והולכה בזר פסולה. Veholacha bezar psulah. And הולכה
holacha we know that's an עבודה, avodah, even by the לבונה levona
we'll assume that's an עבודה avodah and it's invalid by a זר.
zar. So what does he say? When I pick the לבונה levona.
off of this and hand it to you, the כהן, Kohen, I
have now moved the לבונה, levona right, a little bit from wherever
it was here? Unless you scooped your hand right under and I
dropped it in back into your hand, but barring that case, I've
moved it in a way that's getting it closer to the מזבח.
mizbe'ach So it's פסול pasul not because this is a quasi-עבודה avodah
in itself, a type of קמיצה, kmitzah, it's פסול pasul because it's
a type of הולכה. holacha.
Okay, if you're behind me, then it wouldn't be a problem?
Unless you say that it's necessary. So maybe it's not all about
direction, maybe it's about a necessary, right, that the גמרא Gemara had
a discussion about which part of הולכה holacha is considered הולכה.
holacha. For the משנה mishna.
also said that, because like in every room going drawer, exactly. Okay,
so that's what he's saying. So now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אמר רב מרי אף אנן נמי תנינא. Amar Rav Mari,
af anan nami tenina. We also taught similarly. זה הכלל, Zeh haklal,
this was the משנה mishna, we had
earlier, כל הקומץ ונותן בכלי והמוליך והמקטיר, kol hakometz venoten bikli vehamolik
vehamaktir, that anytime, that you can have a פיגול pigul thought when
you're doing the קמיצה, kmitzah, putting it in the vessel, doing הולכה
holacha and doing הקטרה. haktarah. Those are the four primary עבודות avodot
by the קמיצה. kmitzah. The act of the קמיצה, kmitzah, putting it
in the כלי, kli, getting it to the מזבח mizbe'ach and putting
it on the מזבח mizbe'ach, and burning. So now we're going to
analyze this. Why are those the four עבודות avodot of a מנחה?
בשלמא קומץ. Bishlama kometz. I understand why קומץ is an עבודה. avodah.
היינו שוחט. Heinu shochet. This tiny little גמרא Gemara we've been saying
it from the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, but it sort of
says it here almost in passing. קומץ parallels שחיטה. shechitah. It is
the, you know, the sort of act of separating which is getting
you access to that thing that you're going to now be offering
up, blood or the קומץ. מוליך נמי היינו מוליך. Molich nami heinu
molich. Bringing it to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the same way that's an
עבודה avodah by the blood, it's an עבודה avodah by the קמיצה.
kmitzah. מקטיר, burning it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach היינו זורק. heinu zorek.
That's like sprinkling the blood. It's getting the object on the מזבח
mizbeach however it's supposed to go, whether by being thrown like the
blood or burned like the
קומץ. אלא נותן בכלי מאי קעביד? Ella noten bikli mai ka'avid? Why
is placing it in the vessel considered an
עבודה? avodah? אילימא משום דדמי לקבלה, Ileima mishum de-dami lekabbalah, which is
what we've always thought. It's similar like catching the blood in the
vessel. מי דמי? Mi dami? It's not similar. התם ממילא הכא קשקיל
ורמי. Hatam mimmeila, hacha kashakul verami. There it is happening by itself,
here you're placing it in. And if you remember, actually we had
some discussion before that the activity is fundamentally a different activity. It's
true the end result is the same, you've got the thing in
a vessel, but there's one activity called catching and there's another activity
called placing, and they're fundamentally different activities. So you can't say that
it's the same, it's a parallel to קבלה. kabbalah. So why are
you חייב chayiv for putting it in the, or why is that
considered a central עבודה? avodah? אלא משום דכיון דלא סגי ליה דלא
עביד ליה. Ella mishum dekeivan delo sagi lei delo avid lei. Since
you need to do it, right, since the קומץ requires קדושת כלי,
kedushat kli, we're assuming that's true, you know, we haven't discussed that
yet, but we're assuming it's true. So it's necessary. Once it's necessary,
עבודה חשובה היא על כרחך. avodah chashuvah hi alkorchach. It's by definition,
or it's a question whether you read the על כרחך, alkorchach, but
anyway, עבודה חשובה היא, avodah chashuvah hi, it's clearly an important act
because you're doing something necessary. על כרחך משויה ליה כקבלה. Alkorchach meshavei
lei kekabbalah. So the fact that it's necessary makes it a pseudo-קבלה.
kabbalah. Not because it's really parallel, but because it's necessary. So he's
saying, well, if that's true, let's say the same thing by the
gathering of the לבונה. levona You have to... On the one hand,
you could say it's not an עבודה... avodah... And the כהן kohen
shall gather the לבונה. levona So it doesn't describe the act. On
the other hand, you got to get the לבונה levona. off. So
since it's necessary to get the לבונה off and a necessary act
makes it become an עבודה. avodah. Now this is again interesting, you
know, from a classic לומדות lomdus perspective that always has us thinking
about, do I care about the process or do I care about
the end result? And here what's right in here what the גמרא
is basically saying is we start for caring about the end result.
It needs קדושת כלי kedushas kli by the קמיצה. kemitzah. It needs
to get off of the מנחה so it can get to the
מזבח mizbeach by itself. But if I need if the end result
is what I need, then because of the import the only way
you get there is through an activity, that gives weight to the
activity itself and makes the activity defined as an עבודה. avodah. Now
this does not sound like הולכה. holachah. This sounds much more like
I was saying is a quasi-קמיצה, kemitzah, right? Because it's important because
it allows you to get it to the קטורת. ketores. So let's
take a look. Let's finish the sentence and then you can all
ask your questions. הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too, כיון דלא סגיא
דלא עביד לה, keivan d'lo sagi d'lo avid lah, it's you cannot
get around without doing it, without taking the לבונה off the מנחה,
עבודה חשובה היא, avodah chashuvah hi, then it becomes an important act.
על כרחך משוי ליה כהולכה, al korchach meshava lei keholachah, so that
makes it like הולכה holachah now. Therefore you need a כהן. kohen.
Now I would not have added those last words כהולכה. keholachah. I
mean unless what the גמרא is saying is that even if normally
הולכה שלא ברגל holachah shelo b'regel is not הולכה, holachah, or even
if in Michael's case I'm handing it behind me, but once I've
decided that this is an עבודה, avodah, now I have to ask
myself which box to put it in. So since there's some movement
involved, I'll throw it into the עבודה avodah box. If you ask
me,
once I'm going to make it an I mean הולכה holachah box.
If you ask me, once I'm going to make it an עבודה
avodah I would throw it into the קומץ box because it's much
more similar to קמיצה. kemitzah. But in the end I think what's
important about this approach in the גמרא is it doesn't start by
saying, oh yeah, you're moving it and that's הולכה. holachah. It's not
a logical application of the הולכה holachah category. It starts from the
opposite. It's a necessary activity and that makes it an עבודה. avodah.
And therefore it's not כשר שלא בזר, kasher shelo b'zar, which would
also mean by the way, that you could then have a פיגול
pigul. thought while you're doing the gathering of the לבונה, a פיגול
pigul. thought would be significant. Let's finish the גמרא and then you
could ask your questions. לא, says the
גמרא. Nope, that's not a necessary conclusion.
לעולם דדמי לקבלה. l'olam d'dami lekabbalah. Really, by the blood, it's not
the reason the I mean the reason the placing of the קומץ
in the vessel
is an עבודה avodah is not because it's necessary. Necessary doesn't doesn't
up something, you know, upgrade it to an עבודה. avodah. So why
is the placing of the vessel of the קמיצה kemitzah in the
vessel an עבודה? avodah? Because it is really like קבלה. kabbalah. ודקא
קשיא לך, v'deka kashya lach, you said, oh, they're not the same.
התם ממילא הכא קשקיל ורמי. hasam mimila hacha kashakil v'ramei. One happens
by itself and the other is an activity of one is catching
and the other is putting in. Give me a break. מכדי, mechdi,
let's take a look. רווייהו קדושת כלי הוא. ravaihu kedushas kli hu.
Both of them are getting it into the כלי. kli. They're activities
of how do you get the thing in the כלי. kli. Okay?
מה לי ממילא מה לי קשקיל ורמי? ma li mimila ma li
kashakil v'ramei? What do I care if it happens by itself, what
do I care if you do it actively? So this is actually
a great גמרא, because this גמרא is saying, what makes something an
עבודה? avodah? We know the ארבע עבודות arba avodos by by a
קרבן. korban? Okay? But but after that what makes something an עבודה
avodah if it's not explicit? Does it have to basically be an
application of those four defined categories or can I say that any
necessary activity in you know getting the דם or the קומץ or
the מתיר to the מזבח becomes an עבודה? avodah? So this is
it. If you say necessary activity, then you'll say that it applies
to the gathering of the לבונה and you'll פסל possel a זר
zar and you'll say you thought you can have a פיגול pigul,
thought then. But if you say no, no, no, it's only defined
activities, just because you need the end result doesn't make the activity
important, then you won't say the gathering of the לבונה. That could
be כשר בזר. kasher b'zar. And then what you'll say is, what
defines the parallel of קבלה kabbalah from a קרבן to to a
מנחה would be the placing in a vessel. Not exactly the same
but close enough. It's almost like an אב av and a תולדה
toldah on שבת. Shabbos. Okay? It's close enough, doesn't have to be
the exact same. The same way קמיצה kemitzah is not the exact
same as שחיטה. shechitah. Okay? So that but the difference is is
something an עבודה avodah because it's it fits in four defined boxes
or can something be an עבודה avodah starting from the principle that
it's a necessary activity? Now there were a couple of questions. Michael,
you had a question? No. Just think of another question.
Yes, James. Before before הולכה holachah in זבחים Zevachim we talk about
like if the זר zar picks it up and he puts it
back where he got it and it'll be okay if a כהן
kohen came later because... Right.
Which types of things are reversible or not. Right. Is that relevant
here? It is. We talked about it a little bit before about
the reversing the שמאל. smol.
Again, is it going to come up later? I'll have to check.
But right, there's a question, I mean it's one thing to say
that it's פסול, posul, it's another thing how פסול posul is it
and can you reverse it or not?
Yeah.
Just point out that this is really great.
Oh you think? In what way?
In terms of the idea that the things that are necessary for
being able to accomplish the end goals
of a...
it makes sense.
The ends justify the
means. Right. But the things that are necessary in order for me
to do the עבודה avoda become כלי עבודה kelei avoda themselves. So,
you know, it's not just about following הלכה halacha as written, but
my higher end goals of קדושים תהיו kedoshim tihiyu or whatever else.
The things that I need to do to achieve that are in
fact an עבודה avoda or a fulfillment.
Mm-hmm. The end sanctifies the means.
Very nice.
Yes. So I'm sorry, so we're saying that either way, putting the
gathering the לבונה is an עבודה? avoda?
That's a מחלוקת. machlokes. It depends how you define עבודה. avoda. Do
you define עבודה avoda as starting from the principle of a necessary
activity? Then it is an עבודה. avoda. Do you define an עבודה
avoda as something that derives from the four classic categories? Then it
isn't an עבודה.
avoda. But then we'd say either way, it's
either הלכה halacha or it's קבלה, kabbala, so either way it's the
same? No.
הלכה halacha and קבלה kabbala works for why why putting the קומץ
in the כלי kli is an עבודה. avoda. That's an עבודה, avoda,
but not the לבונה. The question is, is the קומץ in the
כלי kli because it's a logical extension of קבלה kabbala and then
gathering the לבונה is not a logical extension of anything?
Or is it
because it's necessary and then gathering the לבונה because it's also necessary
and becomes an עבודה? avoda? So that remains a debate. Okay, let's
see now the next משנה. Now we are going to move on
to
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and the two lambs, which I mentioned
before. שחט שני כבשים לאכול אחת מן החלות למחר.
shachas sheni kevasim leechol achas min
hachalos lemachar.
You slaughtered the two lambs with the intent to eat one of
the loaves of bread of the שתי הלחם shtei halechem tomorrow. Okay,
so wait a
minute. Let me just check רש"י Rashi for a second here. Okay,
so in that הקטיר שני בזיכין hikter sheni bazichin
or you offered up the two בזיכין of the לבונה לאכול אחד
מן הסדרים למחר leechol echad min hasidarim lemachar to eat one of
the columns or even one of the loaves tomorrow. רבי יוסי אומר
Rabbi Yosi omer אותה החלה ואותו הסדר שחישב עליו פיגול. osoh hachalla
veosoh haseder shechishav alav pigul.
So that one loaf by the שתי הלחם shtei halechem or the
whole column by the bread, it could even be one loaf by
the bread, anyway, that one thing does become פיגול pigul. because you
thought about that, וחייבין עליו כרת, vechayavin alav kores,
and you get כרת. kores. והשני פסול ואין בו כרת. vehasheni pasul
veein bo kores.
But the remains, the second loaf of bread or the second column
of bread by the שתי הלחם shtei halechem is invalid, but since
your thought wasn't about the other loaf or the other column, then
it does not become פיגול. pigul It's just פסול, pasul, it's not
פיגול. pigul, Your thought wasn't about it itself. So again you see
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, has a narrow definition of פיגול, pigul.
right? He narrowed it before about מתיר המתר, matir hamatir, he's narrowing
it here. וחכמים אומרים זה וזה פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. vachachamim omrim
zeh vazeh pigul vechayavin alav kores. They're both פיגול. pigul, So the
question is when you think about one thing, does it make the
whole group into פיגול pigul or just that object? The other thing
to think about is it said that you had your thought when
you were doing both lambs or both בזיכי לבונה. Let's say you
had your thought when you were only doing one lamb or only
one בזיך לבונה. bazich levona. So that would be the question of
what?
If
you had your thought only at one of the two activities, and
here they're equivalent, it's not like the קומץ and the לבונה. They're
equivalent activities, the two lambs, the two בזיכי לבונה. But we're not
dealing with that now. We're dealing with does it apply just to
the single object you thought about or the whole collective? So let's
see what the גמרא says. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, רב
הונא Rav Huna says, אומר היה רבי יוסי, omer haya Rabbi Yosi,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi used to say, notice again the אומר היה
רבי יוסי. omer haya Rabbi Yosi. Okay, before it was אמר ריש
לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, just אמר רב הונא. amar Rav Huna. Everybody
is speculating as to רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi reasonings. אומר היה רבי
יוסי פיגול בירך של ימין לא נתפגל הירך של שמאל. omer haya
Rabbi Yosi pigul beyerech shel yamin lo nitpagel hayerech shel smol. רבי
יוסי, it's not just because they're the loaves are separate objects, which
is what I would have thought. And if you think about one
loaf, maybe that loaf is פיגול, pigul? not the other loaf. Even
if it's physically the same object, if I plan on eating the
right thigh of this animal tomorrow, then the left thigh is actually
פסול pasul but not פיגול. Okay, it only applies to the כזית
kazayis or the object that I was specifically thinking about.
So to make a whole קרבן like פיגול, you'd have to think
about eating the whole קרבן?
Right. So very bizarre, and I would not have inferred that from
רבי יוסי in the משנה. רבי יוסי in the משנה, I would
have said they're physically separate objects. Okay, so let's see what the
גמרא says. מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? איבעית אימא סברא
ואיבעית אימא קרא. ibayis eima svara veibayis eima kra. Either logic or
פסוק, pasuk, I could argue that it only applies to exactly what
you were thinking about. איבעית אימא סברא, ibayis eima svara, I could
say it's logic. לא עדיפא מחשבה ממעשה הטומאה. lo adifa machshava mimaaseh
hatumah. So here's a great statement because this is really what פיגול
is about. Thought is like action. So okay, thought's like action. So
what happens if I did this activity with just the right thigh?
If I actually left the right thigh too late, it wouldn't make
the left thigh into נותר. notar. So when I think about the
right side, right thigh, why does it make the left side into
פיגול? Okay, so thought is like action. So what happens if I
did this activity with just the right thigh? If I actually kept
the right thigh too late, it wouldn't make the left thigh into
נותר *notar*. So when I think about the right thigh, why does
it make the left thigh into פיגול *pigul*? Okay, so thought is
no better than action. מחשבה ממעשה *machshava mimaseh*. הא טומאה *ha tumah*,
אילו נטמא איבר *ilu nitma eiver*. So let's think it was a
טומאה *tumah* case. If one side became
טמא *tamei*, would the other one become טמא *tamei*? So if your
thought is about one object, fine, that object is like you did
it. But why should it affect the other side? ואיבעית אימא קרא
*ve'iba'it eima kra* or I'll give you a פסוק *pasuk*. והנפש האוכלת
ממנו עונה תישא *vehanefesh ha'ochelet mimenu avona tisa*. When you eat from
it, ממנו *mimenu*, from it and לא מחברו *lo mechaveiro*, not from
this other thing, the thing you didn't actually think about. Only when
you eat from the thing you thought about. So now he is
not limited to when it's physically a separate object, it will only
apply to the exact thing you thought about. אתיבי רב נחמן לרב
הונא *etivei Rav Nachman le-Rav Huna*. רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* challenged רב
הונא *Rav Huna*. We have a ברייתא *baraita*, לעולם אין בו כרת
*le'olam ein bo kareit*, there will never be כרת *kareit* when you
have a thought and make something into פיגול *pigul* עד שיפגל בשתיהן
בכזית *ad sheyefagel bishteihen bikezayit* until you have a פיגול *pigul* with
both of them with a כזית *kezayit*. What are the both of
them? So this is basically a כזית *kezayit* of... one minute...
right, so this is the two loaves of bread that you're bringing
the two sheep, it's the שתי הלחם בשבועות *shtei halechem biShavuot* and
you are planning on eating a כזית *kezayit* from both like both
loaves combined. So it said that you have to have a מחשבה
*machshava* of both loaves which presumably בשתיהן *bishteihen*, which would mean half
a כזית *kezayit* of each would combine. Now what's that coming to
explain?
But not a כזית *kezayit* of each one of them.
A כזית *kezayit* of each certainly.
But you don't even need a כזית *kezayit* of each one of
them.
You don't correct, you don't need a כזית *kezayit* of each one.
Exactly. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: בשתיהן אין באחת מהן
לא *bishteihen in be'achat mehen lo*. So only if you have a
thought about both of them are you חייב *chayav* when you eat
from both of them. But if you have a thought about one
of them, you're not חייב *chayav* when you eat from the other.
So
מני *mani*, who is this? אילימא רבנן *ilima rabanan*, if it's the
רבנן *rabanan*, אפילו באחת מהן נמי *afilu be'achat mehen nami*, even if
your thought was just about one of them, you'd be חייב *chayav*
if you ate from the other one. So אלא פשיטא *ela peshita*
it must be רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*. Okay, it's רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yose*. And now what? אי אמרת בשלמא חד גופא הוא משום הכי
מצטרף *i amarta bishlama chad gufa hu mishum hachi mitztaref*. If you
say, here's the argument, a very elegant argument and we'll end with
this, if you say that רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* in principle would
say when you have like two thighs of an animal, when something
is one unit, a פיגול *pigul* thought from one affects the other,
then and the reason he's arguing in the משנה *mishna* is because
the breads are separate units. So it's a question of do we
define something as one unit or of two units. If that's the
issue, I could say that your thought could also combine them. So
I could say that the two breads are different units, so פיגול
*pigul* for one doesn't affect the other. But if I think in
my mind I'm going to eat a half a כזית *kezayit* from
this and a half a כזית *kezayit* from this, in my mind
I'm making them one unit, like one collection. And therefore, right, that
would create פיגול *pigul* on both of them. That makes sense. Okay,
if I fundamentally hold that there's an idea of one unit and
when things are one unit, one כזית *kezayit* affects the entirety.
They're like objects, right? You couldn't have a half a כזית *kezayit*
of the bread and a half a כזית *kezayit* of the meat.
Correct. Okay, so משום הכי מצטרף *mishum hachi mitztaref*, therefore they would
combine. Let's just read the first line, we'll review this tomorrow. אלא
אי אמרת תרי גופי נינהו *ela i amarta trei gufei ninhu*. But
if you say that in the case of the thighs, meaning even
if something is physically the same, we always look at everything that
is distinct, right? It doesn't matter if they're physically the same, everything
is distinct from everything else. So if that's true, מי מצטרפי *mi
mitztarfei*? How could it combine? How could a half a כזית *kezayit*
of this loaf combine with a half a כזית *kezayit* of that
loaf if they're physically distinct? So we rushed through that, we'll repeat
that tomorrow, but on such a short דף *daf*, I didn't want
to end behind. Okay, so to be continued tomorrow.